Next we've been promised another fireside chat so you'll see the
furniture coming back but it sounds to me more like a master class with another
global superstar here to discuss the art and science of decision-making with
Alec Ellison the founder of Outvest Capital please welcome the economist
author and Nobel Prize winner Daniel Kahneman so welcome Danny or should I say
welcome home to Jerusalem so I want to provide a little bit of background for
people on your work by telling a little story so once upon a time there were
experts in fields ranging from medicine to finance to professional sports scouting
and then along came two professors at the Hebrew University Danny Kahneman here
and his partner Amos Torski and they made observations about systematic mistakes
we all make as humans mistakes you can predict effectively they became connoisseurs
of error through their work Danny and Amos became founders and pioneers in the
field of behavioral economics and as you heard for this work Danny won the 2002
Nobel prize in economics
I could spend our entire time here providing accolades for Danny's work but I'll just
personalize it I've read his 2011 bestseller thinking fast and slow three times I know that
makes you think I'm slow and Michael Lewis did a did a piece a book called the undoing project which I've read twice because Michael Lewis felt he had to understand who was behind the change in understanding of how in the specific case if you're familiar with
and professional sports scouting and money ball so Danny your work has been truly disruptive people here talk about disruption all the time but you may be the greatest disruptor ever had up on the stage here so
so let's get into our discussion we have an audience full of investors and entrepreneurs they all need to make
decisions with less than perfect information given all the systematic cognitive biases you've documented how can they make decisions when they are necessarily not fully informed and have to use some intuition
well all decisions are made with only partial information and and decisions don't have to me to be perfect in order to work and most decisions are imperfect and they still work so what we can do is improve things at the margin and improving things that the margin can be done in multiple ways and this is what we're studying now so let's let's hear how are some of the
ways to improve decisions at the margin you know there is a question about intuition you know whether you're for intuition or against intuition it's absolutely clear that intuition can be marvelous and it's also absolutely clear that intuition is often wrong and and there are a few things that we know we know about the conditions under which intuition is likely to be right and I think we know something about how to
how to improve it and we know that it's likely to be right and we know that it's likely to be right if you've had a lot of experience and if the word is sufficiently regular for that experience to be worth something so for example I do not believe intuition in intuition in the stock market because the stock market doesn't have the regularity that it takes but where intuition is worthwhile is worth having and it's worth having in many situations what you really want to
what you want to do I think is to delay it is to delay it until you have all the information the problem with wrong intuitions they tend to arise very quickly they tend to be premature and you are better off if you collect information first and collect all the information in a systematic way and only then allow yourself to take a global view and to have an intuition about the global view this applies in
in many domains so take as delay as much as you can before making that judgment okay let's talk about optimism versus delusion
let's talk about optimism versus delusion you view optimism as perhaps the most significant cognitive bias we humans have people overestimate their abilities and they underestimate the odds they face yet you view optimism as such a blessing that I quote from your book if you were allowed one wish for your child seriously
consider wishing him or her optimism so and you also refer to optimism as the engine of capitalism so is there a difference between overconfidence and what I'll call healthy optimism
so is there a difference between overconfidence and what I'll call healthy optimism
well you know that in the first place when you when you look at great successes great successes when you look backwards were always due to somebody being crazily over optimistic or delusional even delusional
actually you don't get too big successes without taking unreasonable risks
and so if you look ex-entity the best advice to people is don't do it but the few people who don't follow good advice they tend to be responsible for the successes most of the people who don't follow good advice don't do very well so on average optimism you know the kind that leads to great successes on average it tends to
lead to failure but the occasional successes and that's where we speak of the engine of capitalism for society as a whole it's very good that we have crazy optimist so we've got a bunch of delusional entrepreneurs in the audience and maybe some delusional investors but we all benefit as a society
it's kind of almost the opposite of moral hazard in a way
yeah so you know a related question is given that there's so much entrepreneurial activities in the technology field here
how can humans properly assess technology which can move at an exponential pace
when we have really been conditioned through evolution to adapt to much slower changes
how do you think about that dynamic
well you know I think there are many people futurists like Ray Kurzweil who believe that I mean the fact is that technology seems to be developing exponentially
now people are really not exponential we have adapted we're linear and we're not suited to exponential development
my guess is there's going to be a tremendous amount of dislocation and the problems are likely to be social not technological
it's how society is going to adjust to that level of technological speed
but do you think investors may sometimes underestimate the speed of adoption because of this exponential change when you when something really catches on like the videos we saw a few minutes ago
well I mean you know it's not I think that investors as a whole probably overestimate the speed of adoption
but the very successful investing except for our companies are those who underestimate it you know
it really depends whether you look at things from you know accidentally or exposed and you get very different pictures
ok I want to turn to to start up nation and I don't think many people here realize the role that Danny has played
how many hands here have been in the Israel Defense Forces quite a few
quite a few so over 60 years ago when you were in the IDF you develop personality tests to replace interviewing to assess recruits in order to channel them into the proper units and roles
and indeed as I understand there was a so-called Kahneman score that people were assigned and I also understand it was so successful that it survived to the present day with some relatively minor adjustments
so now within the Israeli technology ecosystem there's a tendency to often to recruit people based on which army units they were in which means that people are often being recruited based on a test that you developed 60 plus years ago
yeah well actually it wasn't a test we what I did then was to modify the interviewing system and and the key idea in the modification and that was about 63 years ago was to delay intuition
to make to make to make the interviewers collect information and attributes one at a time and really try not to develop a global view of whether this is going to be a good soldier or not until all the information was in
and these days I'm engaged in writing a book about decision making where actually our motto is that options and decision making are very much like candidates and that there ought to be a way of applying what we know about personnel selection and we know a lot to decision making in other domains
now as I understand one of the things you were trying to address was interviewers hiring in their own image
correct so this was a way of turning the judgment into a more of an what we might call an algorithmic process today
not let the interviewer know exactly
I mean actually you know that interviewing story that that you're telling and my very early experience in psychology that was my first experience in psychology is again people wanted to have intuitions the previous interviewing system that we replace was a system where people just talk to the individual and try to form a global impression
and the problem is when you're interviewing in that way you form a global impression much too quickly and the global impression is likely to be wrong and if you delay forming a global impression until you collect information on specific topics you end up with an intuition which is far more accurate and that were the lesson of 60 years ago and it turns out that it's been widely accepted in the domain of human resources and personnel selection
and applying it to decision making more broadly is an interesting exercise and that's the one in which I'm engaged these days
so so your message to entrepreneurs who feel a rush to build their teams is to really step back and make sure that they're hiring based on whether it's formal test but real data delay the decisions and not the five minute interview
Well I mean you know that advice of being quite systematic about building a field it turns out that the most successful companies are really doing that and they're investing a great deal Google I think is the best example that I know about about personnel selection and they're very systematic they spend a huge amount of money on it
they there are multiple interviews the interviews the interviews are all organized and structured and independent that that's a very important part of good decision making and is keeping your sources of information as independent as possible
so let's elaborate on this I think some of your current work is on different ways of tuning out the noise
yeah
could you elaborate on that well there is an enormous amount of noise in decision making I mean we we became aware of that the extent of that actually in an insurance company in asking by how much do underwriters who look at exactly the same risk differ in their assessments and we compared that to the
and we compared that to the expectations of the executives and the differences among underwriters were about five times as large as expected by the executives and it turns out that this is true wherever you go we now have a sort of saying wherever there is judgment there is noise and there is more of it than you think because people underestimate the extent to which others agree with them and underestimate the amount of the extent of differences
very consistently and very systematically
that would suggest in entrepreneurial environments taking the time or in corporate environments taking the time to to almost write down areas of agreement to avoid this this cognitive bias
well I mean you know that the one danger in all of this is you don't want to paralyze yourself by too much analysis and you don't want to paralyze yourself by too many bureaucratic procedures and you don't want to paralyze yourself by too many bureaucratic procedures
so finding the best way to combine a disciplined approach to decision making with something that is not too bureaucratic and the decision makers will feel is a help to them rather than a sort of a bureaucratic constraint that's a tough exercise
that's a tough exercise so changing taxes slater now so the implications of your work have driven the use of algorithms and most famously and most in popular fame in sports but again in finance medicine we talked about zebra technologies earlier there's been a lot of talk of AI here using of algorithms algorithms algorithms algorithms and of course there's a potential downside in terms of
loss of employment in certain fields but greater employment in certain fields but greater employment in others do you have a perspective on how fast this might occur or which fields may be the most vulnerable
well I mean you know this is happening at a tremendous rate and it's and the people are being displaced and we're at greatest risk of being displaced I think are in white collar professions so there are disciplines that are disappearing dermatology dermatological diagnosis is going to be done better on the phone than when people do it
uh there are forms of cancer that are far better detected by AI that are far better detected by AI than when people do it
uh there are forms of cancer that are far better detected by AI than when people do it
uh there are forms of cancer that are far better detected by AI than when people do it I mean you know you know this is happening at a tremendous rate and it's and the people are being displaced and we're at greatest risk of being displaced I think are in white collar professions I think are in white collar professions
So there are disciplines that are disappearing. Dermatology, dermatological diagnosis is going to be done better on the phone than when people do it. There are forms of cancer that are far better detected by AI than they are by radiologists. A lot of the legal profession and legal profession, the legal in the legal field, collecting precedence and collecting
relevant laws is something that is going to be automated. So the extent of this, very likely I think people are underestimating it and people in the professions involved think they're unreplaceable, but actually more people are going to be replaced than think they are.
I have one last question. We talked at the outset of your being one of the greatest disruptors of the last generation.
legacy to be. Is it as a disruptor or one who gave us insights that we never understood before? The work is so far ranging.
You know, it's a question I've never asked myself. The one thing I would actually like to leave as my legacy is one is a way to change the way the controversies are conducted in my field. And I would like the controversies. I invented
the term adversarial collaboration between people who disagree on a way of doing things. And not that there is much hope for it, but that's what I would wish my legacy to be.
Agreeing disagreeably. Thank you so much, Danny. What a pleasure.
What a pleasure.